Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic Records Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic Records
1926/1968
This collection contains records from the Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic. The collection has 3 series: Staff Conferences, Psychic Research, and Teaching and Course Material.
2.09 linear feet (5 boxes)
Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic (Baltimore, Md.)
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1936.0001
There are no formal records of acquisition. However, the records belonged to Dr. Oskar Diethelm during his affiliation with Johns Hopkins Medical School, where he was an Instructor and Associate in Psychiatry from 1927-1932 and Associate Professor of Psychiatry from 1932-1936.
Box 2 folders 3, 4, 6-8, 17, 19 and Box 3 folder 1 are restricted due to PHI (private health information). The folders have been removed from Box 2 and 3 and stored separately.
The Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic was opened in 1913 and is a division of Johns Hopkins Hospital in Baltimore. Dr. Adolf Meyer was Professor of Psychiatry and Director of the Psychiatric Clinic of Johns Hopkins Hospital beginning in 1909. At the Phipps Clinic, the leadership of Meyer shaped developments along two mutually supporting lines. First, Meyer strove to gain scientific recognition of the functioning human being as the central feature in psychiatry and towards insuring a practical acknowledgement of, and a realistic dealing with, the psychological modes of human functioning. To this end, he developed and taught a philosophical orientation to psychiatry known as psychobiology. Second, in the practical work of the clinic, Meyer insisted upon a pluralistic and pragmatic collection of all available facts about a given patient as the basis for action. The voluminous case records gathered became the main research material of the Phipps Clinic.
Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic (Baltimore, Md.); Diethelm, Oskar, 1897-; Phipps, Henry, 1839-1930; Johns Hopkins Hospital; Meyer, Adolf, 1866-1950; Psychobiology; Women psychics; Clairvoyants; Johns Hopkins University; Spiritualism; Parapsychology; Garrett, Eileen J. (Eileen Jeanette), 1893-1970; Rorschach Test; Levy, David M. (David Mordecai), 1892-
This collection contains records from the Henry Phipps Psychiatric Clinic. There are 3 series in this collection.
Staff Conferences: These were attended by the entire staff of psychiatrists and residents every morning six days a week. Dr. Diethelm as Chief Resident Physician selected the speaker who was to present the discussion. Dr. Meyer presided and occasionally spoke during the entire conference. Often there were invited guests who presented on specific topics, such as psychobiology, history, and psychoanalysis. Nearly every patient admitted was discussed at some time during the staff conferences.
Psychic Research: This series consists of transcripts of interviews conducted by Dr. Meyer with three women. These people professed to be psychics, and the interviews were conducted along these lines.
Teaching and Course Material: These documents include some of Dr. Meyer’s material that he used in teaching psychiatry to first through fourth year students at Johns Hopkins University, such as examinations, outlines, and handouts prepared by Meyer for distribution to students about various aspects of psychiatry.
- Staff Conferences
  - Background information about staff conferences, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Discussion of panic, 1930 (Box 1)
  - General topics, education and psychiatry, delinquency, schizophrenic deterioration, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Introductory staff presentation by Adolf Meyer, 1932 (Box 1)
  - Historical discussion, Dr. Rosett’s description of his neurological research, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Meyer on symbolization and Dr. Diethelm on panic, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Interview with Dr. Kubie, Dr. Diethelm on Rorschach and handwriting analysis and Dr. Meyer on psychobiology, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Meyer on teaching first year psychopathology course and and Dr. Meyer on teaching staff, 1934 (Box 1)
  - Teaching psychobiology, historical review, and Dr. Guttmacher on court psychiatry, 1934 (Box 1)
  - General discussion, Dr. Meyer on psychobiology and behaviorism, and social medicine, 1934 - 1935 (Box 1)
  - Psychoanalysis, Dr. Barbu on state hospitals, and Dr. Meyer on teaching, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Introductory staff meeting, Dr. Meyer on teaching, and Dr. Meyer on current psychiatric concepts, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Description of treatment and Dr. Rado, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Compulsion neurosis, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Case presentations, Dr. Diethelm on chronic alcoholism, and clinical description of schizophrenia, 1933; 1936 (Box 2)
  - Relationship to state hospitals and Frank Leiton, 1932 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED case presentations, three case descriptions, and form for test for hospital attendant, Undated (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED notes on cases examined at Spring Grove State Hospital by Dr. Barbu, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Report of Dr. Meyer on Spring Grove and Springfield State Hospitals, 1932 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED description of patient, 1929 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED legal case, defendant testimony by Dr. Diethelm, 1929 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED case presentation by resident, 1929 (Box 2)
- Psychic Research
  - Psychic research, Miss Cross interviewed by Dr. Meyer, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Psychic research, Mrs. Garrett interviewed by Dr. Meyer, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Garrett, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Garrett, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Garrett, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Garrett, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Garrett, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Garrett, 1932 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED Mrs. Garrett, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Mrs. Garrett, 1932 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED Dr. David Levy’s results of Rorschach Test given to Mrs. Garrett and related material, 1933 (Box 2)
  - RESTRICTED psychic research, Mrs. Massingbird-Rogers interviewed by Dr. Meyer, 1940 (Box 3)
  - Mrs. Massingbird-Rogers, 1940 - 1941 (Box 3)
  - Mrs. Massingbird-Rogers, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Mrs. Massingbird-Rogers, 1941 (Box 3)
- Teaching and Course Material
  - First through fourth years, 1926 - 1932 (Box 3)
  - First and second years, Undated (Box 3)